These two people were not anybody, because it was Sweden's then Prime Minister Olof Palme and his wife Lisbeth Palme.
They walk along Sveavägen south and when they come to Adolf Fredrik's church street they cross the way and continue the walk.
When the clock beats 23:21:30, what happened that didn't happen.
The couple was now at Tunnelgatan at a store called Dekorima.
Suddenly a man shows up behind the couple, in his hand he has a gun.
The thunder of two shots that go by oaks through the streets this February evening.
The first shot hit Olof Palme in the back The second shot turned his back on his wife Lisbeth.
The perpetrator flees the place up the stairs towards Malmskillnadsgatan and then down the street of David Bagare before he disappears without a trace.
Palme falls lifeless down to the ground, the shot had killed him immediately.
After the shots were fired against the Palme couple, the first call came in to the alarm center 23:22:20.
And the talks continued to roll in to the alarm center during the evening.
This whole event would raise so many questions, questions that people would ask themselves for several years to come.
What really happened?
00:06 So Palme is declared dead at the hospital.
His wife Lisbeth had managed with minor injuries, the ball had just turned her back.
00:20 Sweden's National News Agency TT sent out a Flashtellegram with the text “Olof Palme is dead”
00:45 So Sweden's Deputy Prime Minister Ingvar Carlsson arrives at Rosenbad, that is the building where the government is located.
01:10 At night, the music was interrupted in Sweden's Radio and instead the voice is heard by the report Jan Ström which reads the following message to the public:
Since this message was broadcast in the middle of the night, the majority of Swedes were completely unaware of what had happened.
But now the hunt for the killer of Sweden's prime minister was underway.
The day after the murder happened, they began to investigate the crime scene.
Unfortunately, they did not find much trace of the perpetrator, but they found the two bullets that were fired.
One bullet was found in the morning on March 1st the day after the murder on Sveavägen's western sidewalk.
It was the ball that had turned at Lisbeth's back.
The second bullet was found on March 2nd at the Jalusigallret to the stairs leading down to the subway on Tunnelgatan.
It was the ball that killed Olof Palme.
The bullets were of the type .357 Magnum metal piercing from manufacturer Winchester western.
The weapon itself used by the killer is not entirely clear, but the most common weapon used for this type of ammunition
is a revolver from manufacturer Smith & Wesson.
But there are also other manufacturers of weapons with the same type of caliber.
For example.
Colt, Ruger & Co, Taurus and others.
During the investigation, the police have tested 788 different weapons to try to find similarities to the bullets fired on the Palme couple.
Unfortunately, it is basically impossible to know which weapon has been used.
But before we continue I have to
In 1986, the Internet may not exist in Sweden yet, but it does now and as you probably know, the Internet is everywhere.
When you are surfing the web, your internet provider sees what you do and what you are looking for.
Like a small uninvited guest that you have not asked for.
But don't worry - NordvPN helps you keep your internet traffic anonymous and also protect you from going to dangerous websites.
So that you can enjoy your entertainment safely.
Go to nordvpn.com/snabbfakta and use the code quick facts to get a huge discount on a 2-year subscription 4 free months!
Link is in the description!
You can also use Nordvpn's service to virtually change which country you are in.
This is good if, for example, you would like to read news or watch a movie on a streaming service that is not available in your country.
Go to nordvpn.com/snabbfakta and use the code quick facts
Then - back to 1986.
After the police interrogated all the witnesses who were around the crime scene that night, a description of the perpetrator was sought.
The murder must have been committed by a man who was between 175-190 cm long.
The man should be between 30 - 50 years old.
The man had a dark jacket or rock and a cap or a hat on his head.
According to some witnesses, the man moved clumsily and limped forward.
According to other witnesses, he moved smoothly and easily.
Okay, so we have a description of the perpetrator.
On March 6, 1986 - thus about 1 week after the murder, the police had produced a phantom picture of the perpetrator.
After the phantom image was published in almost every news magazine throughout the country, the tips began to hail in to the police.
The phantom picture gave between 7000 - 8000 tips to the police.
However, this phantom image has afterwards been very questioned.
It is based on a testimony from a person who was in Smala alley, about 350-400 m from where the murder happened.
According to the witness, it was between 23:30 - 23:40 when the witness saw the possible perpetrator.
Since the murder took place 23:21, this time span between 23:30 and 23:40 is, according to a later police investigation, far too late for it to be likely.
Today, you don't even think the Phantom image represents the killer.
Anyway, the police have followed a lot of different tracks over the years to find the one or those who murdered Olof Palme.
Remember that this video is a summary so I will not go through any possible perpetrators and tracks,
If we start with the 33-year-old.
The 33-year-old was a man named Victor Gunnarsson.
He really hated Olof Palme.
He was a member of the "European Workers' Party" - an organization that was very critical of Olof Palme.
He also liked weapons.
The tip about the so-called 33-year-old came to the police the day after the murder.
One woman told me she had been to a cafe named Mon Chéri on Kungsgatan at 22 the same night as the murder happened.
During the time he spent at the cafe, the man had talked loudly about his hatred against Olof Palme.
Several other people must have also advised the police about the same man and they have also mentioned the "33-year-old "'s Palmehat.
On March 8, 1986, he was picked up by the police and taken in for questioning.
He was released the same evening but already 4 days later he was taken into interrogation again and now the police began to become suspicious.
He told me in the interview that he was at Mon Cheri the same night as the murder took place.
In the cafe he had talked to 3 different women and even 2 men.
He was questioned by police on May 28, 1986, 2 months after the murder of Palme where they wondered, he was during the murder night on February 28.
According to Christer Pettersson himself, he had visited a club on Oxtorgsgatan called BK Oxen.
He arrived at the club around 19:00 in the evening and went home at 22:00.
He went to the Central and took the commuter train to Rotebro.
He was at home in his home at 23:30 and went to bed.
In the morning he went and picked up the newspaper and then got the knowledge of the murder of Olof Palme.
However, the police were very suspicious of Pettersson and about 1 year later, tips began to fall into the police that Christer Pettersson was similar to the Phantom image that the police had previously published.
He was called in for questioning several times and on December 14, 1988, Lisbeth Palme pointed out Christer Pettersson as the perpetrator in a recorded testimony.
A witness confrontation is a measure that the police can take when investigating a crime and has a strong suspected offender and wants to investigate whether a witness can recognize the perpetrator.
Then you can, for example,
Set up several different people in a row without saying which of them is suspected of the police.
Then it is up to the witness to point out the perpetrator.
After Christer Pettersson was designated by Lisbeth as her husband's murderer, Christer was arrested and
In July 1989, Christer Pettersson was sentenced to life imprisonment for the murder of Prime Minister Olof Palme.
He had quit his work for the evening and went home at 23:20.
When he was on Sveavägen south, he hears a bang about 20 meters away.
Then he sees a person lying on the ground and blood on the ground and that there were people around.
When he arrives, Lisbeth tells him that the perpetrator had a dark blue cover jacket.
Police arrive at the scene and ask "in which direction?"
Stig, who at the time sat down stands up and points with the whole hand towards the tunnel and says "in that direction!"
Then Stig finds that he might have mentioned something about the dark blue cover jacket.
Stig then runs after the police officers he has seen running into the alley, without catching them.
The police were gone.
He then returns to the crime scene.
He himself believes that the signal element left afterwards, that they are looking for a man with a dark rock and cap can apply to him.
Because that's what he was wearing during the evening.
According to Stig, he remained at the crime scene for a while before returning to Skandia about 23:40.
He called his wife, took a coffee and then took the night bus home.
What makes his statement a little suspicious is the following:
And according to witnesses, no one has even seen him at the crime scene.
So what did he really do during the 20 minutes between 23:20 and 23:40?
Many of Stig's friends and relatives describe him as a person with a great need for confirmation.
He exaggerated and often spread his stories.
He spiced his stories a little extra to portray himself as a little better.
So it may be that Stig is trying to portray himself as a bit of a hero in this context
Or could it be so ... that he tries to mislead the cops?
It was discussed in 1986 by members of the police investigation into Stig Engström was a possible perpetrator.
But he was put aside and the suspicions against Stig cooled off while the police focused on other tracks.
34 years later.
The police investigation into who murdered Olof Palme is the largest police investigation in Sweden's history and even one of the largest police investigations in the world.
Over 90,000 people have been in the investigation.